2023年底，一条正在印度喜马拉雅山脉建设中的新公路隧道
In late 2023, a new road tunnel under
发生坍塌，
construction in the Indian Himalayas collapsed,
将41名工人困于地下长达两周有余。
trapping 41 workers inside for more than two weeks.
这场事故引发了近年来最紧张的救援行动之一。
It led to one of the most intense rescue operations in recent history.
这次险情是一记巨大的警钟。
This emergency was a huge wakeup call.
随后展开的调查揭露出多项严重失误。
The investigation that followed unearthed multiple failings.
两年后，同一地区的一条铁路隧道终于贯通
Two years later, there was a breakthrough on
——但同样险些酿成悲剧。
a rail tunnel in the same region that also came close to tragedy.
从无视预警信号
From ignoring warning signs
到勘测不足，印度尝试在世界最高山脉中
to inadequate surveys, India's
修建新基础设施的努力，有时危险至极。
attempts to build new infrastructure through the world's biggest mountain range have at times been extremely dangerous.
如今，这个国家又迎来了更艰巨的挑战——史上最长的隧道工程。
Now, the country's begun an even greater challenge, its longest ever tunnel.
而他们再次选择在这里动工。
And once again, they've
decided to build it here.
欢迎来到喜马拉雅山脉，地球上海拔最高、也最为年轻的山脉。
Welcome to the Himalayas, the highest and newest mountain range on Earth.
[snorts]
但我们并不在尼泊尔、西藏，甚至也不在不丹。
But we're not in Nepal, Tibet, or even Bhutan.
这里是印度的北阿坎德邦（Uttarakhand）。
This is Utarakand in India.
这片土地风景绝美，被称为"众神之地"。
It's an area of breathtaking beauty known as the land of the gods.
这里坐落着查尔达姆朝圣胜地（Chota Chardam）——一系列印度教庙宇和圣地。
That's because it's home to the Chota Chardam, a
series of Hindu temples and pilgrimage sites.
每年有数百万朝圣者前来，
Millions of pilgrims travel here every year,
但他们的旅程谈不上顺畅。
but let's just say their journeys aren't exactly straightforward.
现有道路狭窄、仅有单车道，冬季和
The existing roads are narrow with single lanes.
They can become inaccessible in winter
季风季节往往无法通行。
and the monsoon season.
加之该邦超过一半的地区面临高滑坡风险，
While more than half of the state is at high risk of landslides,
这正是一项全长900公里的公路改造工程启动的原因
which is why a 900 km highway project is underway to
——旨在升级沿途道路、改善各圣地之间的交通联系。
upgrade these routes and build better connections between the sites.
通过将道路替换为双车道公路
By replacing them with two-lane highways and tunnels that
并打通隧道绕开最险峻路段，旅行者将能大大缩短行程，
can cut through some of the worst spots, travelers
也更加安全。
are going to be able to take much shorter, safer trips.
尽管这是一项意义重大的基础设施建设，
Although it's a major piece of new infrastructure and
对整个地区和全印度的印度教信众都至关重要，但它通常不会成为国际头条
obviously incredibly important to
——直到2023年11月12日，
the region and Hindus across India, it's
generally not the sort of thing that would make global news until the 12th of November 2023
世界的目光落在了距邦首府约100英里的这处偏远地点。
when the eyes of the world fell on
this remote location around 100 miles from the state capital.
>>
救援行动正在争分夺秒——数名建筑工人自周日上午起被困于印度山中。与此同时，各方正加大力度，
The race is on to rescue construction workers who have been stuck since Sunday morning in India.
试图将41人从这条坍塌的山体隧道中营救出来，
As efforts ramp up
to get 41 people out of this collapsed mountain tunnel,
>>
事故发生前日，隧道入口突然垮塌，工人们正在洞内作业。
men were working inside the tunnel when the entrance gave way yesterday.
>>
一条在建的全长4.5公里隧道
A 4.5 km long tunnel under construction as
在毫无征兆的情况下坍塌。大批工人当时
part of the project caved in
without warning. Dozens of workers were inside
正在其中，顷刻间便被困住。
at the time and within an instant found themselves trapped.
坍塌发生在距南端锡尔基亚拉（Silkiara）入口270米处。
The collapse happened 270 m from the southern entrance at Silkiara.
由于隧道两端尚未贯通，工人们唯一的逃生通道就此被封堵。
And because the tunnel had not yet been joined in the middle, their
only escape route was blocked.
他们与外界唯一的联系，
They had just one connection to the outside world, a
是一条细小的紧急通道，靠它输送空气、食物、
tiny emergency tunnel that
药品和水。
provided them with air, food, medical supplies, and water.
一位国际专家被紧急召来协助救援。
An international expert was called in to help.
他就是阿诺德·迪克斯教授（Professor Arnold Dixs）。
Meet Professor Arnold Dixs.
他当时担任国际隧道与地下空间协会（International Tunneling and Underground Space Association）主席。
He was at the time president of the International Tunneling and Underground Space Association.
"我在WhatsApp上接到了印度总工程师的电话，
So I I got a call from the chief engineer of India on WhatsApp and
他告诉我出了问题，还发来了一些照片，
uh he told me he had a problem. He
sent me some pictures
问我会怎么处理。
and he asked me what I would do and
下一分钟，我就在跟印度总理的首席顾问通话，
the next minute I was talking to the principal adviser to the prime minister of India and
向他解释我认为的最佳方案，
I was explaining why I thought what I thought would be a good idea
然后他们就直接问我能不能'顺道'过去搭把手。"
and then they just asked me if I could pop over and
give him a hand.
阿诺德抵达现场、评估完情况后，救援计划的制定工作正式展开。
Once Arnold arrived at the site and assessed the situation, it
was time to create a rescue plan.
一台奥格机（orga machine）——说白了就是一台大型钻机——被调来开凿逃生通道。
An orga machine, basically a big drill, was brought in to dig an escape route.
但这不是他们唯一的手段，为提高成功率，多种方案同步推进。
But it wasn't the only thing they
tried. Several methods were executed simultaneously to increase their chances of success.
"我们从地面往下打了一口竖井，
We had a vertical drill coming from the surface down, which
就像把一根针插进山里。一支队伍从后方评估，
is like pushing a pin down through the mountain. We
另一支从侧面用隧道掘进机（TBM）切入。
had a team assessing coming from the back. We had a team launching a TBM from the side.
同时，还有一支队伍采用老式采矿方式，紧贴隧道侧壁、边支撑边推进。
And we also had another team working on a very old-fashioned like
这几条线我们同时推进。"
a mining solution hugging
the side of the tunnel and bracing it. And
这几条线我们同时推进。"
we ran all of them concurrently.
最终，救出工人的还是那台奥格机。
Eventually it was the orga that got them out.
嗯，算是吧。
Well, sort of.
它在即将到达目标区域之前发生故障，
It broke down just before reaching the targets area. So
最后是一群矿工用手动钻机完成了剩余的掘进工作。
a group of miners ended up digging the rest of the way using manual drills.
经过17个惊心动魄的日日夜夜，救援人员终于将所有被困者带出了隧道。
And after 17 terrifying days, the
rescuers were able to free everyone in sight.
所幸没有人受重伤，这是莫大的安慰
Now, while it was a huge relief that no one was seriously hurt, this
——但这也是一次真实的警示：在这片区域建设基础设施危机四伏，
was a real warning sign about the dangers of building infrastructure in this area, and
而且这绝非头一次。
it's not the first sign there's been.
听起来难以置信，但这并不是该地区唯一一条险些酿成灾难的隧道。
Believe it or not, this is not the only tunnel in this area to have come close to disaster.
在东南方向约200公里处，同一个邦内的另一条铁路隧道
Around 200 km to the southeast, another tunnel in the same state, this
于2025年4月实现贯通，
time for rail, broke through in April 2025,
但此前遭遇了严重险情
but only after some serious complications. When
——当掘进机推进到5公里处、约三分之一路程时，
the tunnel boring machine reached the 5 km point, about
突然涌出大量地下水。
a third of the way through, there was a sudden gush of water.
据项目总监介绍，那一刻，隧道面临着被淹没
At this moment, according to the project director, the tunnel was at risk of flooding
或坍塌的风险。
or collapsing.
幸好通过一系列纠正措施，他们成功化解了危机。
But they managed to correct it by taking corrective measures.
那么，同一地区两条在建隧道接连出事，
So, is it a coincidence that
真的只是巧合吗？
two tunnels under construction so close together either collapsed or came very close to it?
很可能不是
Well, probably not because
——因为事实证明，在这片山脉开展此类工程，
it turns out that
挑战之大出奇地高。
carrying out this kind of work in these mountains in particular is exceptionally challenging.
首先，这里剪切带（shear zones）遍布
Firstly, there are sheer zones all over the place. That's
——那是板块构造活动在围岩中造成的高应力区域。
where an area of higher strain is formed within
the surrounding rock caused by tectonic activity.
在剪切带附近掘进，可能引发地层失稳、
Tunneling in areas where they're present can
水或泥浆涌入，乃至坍塌。
lead to instability, ingress of water or mud, and even collapse.
其次是隧道穿越的岩石类型，其硬度可能差异极大。
Then there's the type of rock that's being tunnneled through, which
can vary greatly in terms of hardness.
而且往往无法事先预判会遇到哪种岩石。
And it's not always possible to know exactly what kind of rock you're going to encounter.
"这就是来自隧道坍塌现场的实际岩石样本。就算坐在我的桌旁，你也能感觉到它非常松软。"
So this is the actual rock from the tunnel collapse. Even here sitting at my desk, it's very soft.
"这是被推挤到空中数千米高的古老海床，上升速度极为迅猛。"
It's old seabed um raised up thousands of meters into the air get pushed up very rapidly.
"所以你必须非常敬畏这些动态的地质条件。"
So you you need to be very respectful of those dynamic conditions.
"你得保持应变能力，随时准备反应。"
You have to be uh reactive.
"一旦发现情况不如预期，你必须立刻作出应对。"
So if you see it's not behaving how you expect, you have to react to that.
另一个挑战在于，岩石性状会随埋深增加而发生变化。
Another challenge is working with materials that can change the further underground they are.
那些我们在地表看到的岩石，
Those rocks we see up on the surface.
一旦深入山体，就完全不一样了。
They're not behaving like that once you're deep in a mountain.
它们的表现，简直像是另一种物质。
They're they're actually behaving like a quite a different substance altogether.
"我赋予山脉以生命感。"
I attribute the mountains with a sense of life.
"我不把它们看成死的岩石，"
I don't see them as like dead rock.
"而是把它们视为活的生命体，因为"
actually see them as a living thing because
"它们实际上会移动、会挤压、会不按常理出牌，做出各种出人意料的事。"
actually they move and they squeeze and they they misbehave and they do all sorts of things.
这一切意味着，在这里开挖必须格外谨慎，
All of this means you have to be very careful when
否则就会重蹈我们已经见过的那些覆辙。
digging here or run the risk of problems like the ones we've seen.
在一片地震、洪涝、滑坡频发的土地上挖掘隧道，对任何人来说都是艰巨的挑战。
Building tunnels in a territory that's prone to earthquakes, floods,
and landslides would be a tough job for anyone.
但此次坍塌的部分推定原因，遗憾地源于人为因素。
But some of the presumed causes of the collapse were unfortunately man-made.
一位工程地质学家发现了施工粗糙、隧道规范执行松懈的证据。
One engineering geologist found evidence of poor workmanship and
a lax approach to tunneling practices.
一份官方报告显示，施工形变问题未得到妥善处理，
An official report revealed defamations were not properly addressed and
承包商对此前已暴露的隐患存在失职——而这些，在阿诺德第一次进入坍塌隧道时
there was negligence from the contractor towards previous issues and
便一目了然。
these were plain to see as Arnold discovered when he first went into the tunnel after the collapse.
"我走进隧道入口，向坍塌仍在发生的位置走去。
So I've entered the portal and I'm now walking towards where the collapse is still
我数了一下——之前已有21处坍塌痕迹，沿途清晰可见。"
occurring. I count 21 prior collapses. I
can see the scars as I'm walking down through the tunnel.
"我意识到，这件事绝非突如其来。"
And so I realize this hasn't just happened out of the blue.
"问题是系统性的。没有人想过改变施工方法，
There's something systemic wrong. No one's thought about changing the method or
没有人想过调整断面设计，没有人想过改变支护体系。
no one's thought about changing the profile or
这实在太糟糕了。"
no one's thought about changing the um the support system. It was awful.
虽然近来困难重重，但这个国家的隧道建设者们过去也有过成功案例。
They might have experienced difficulties lately, but tunnelers in this country have had some success in the past.
印度已在喜马拉雅山脉建成一条9公里长的公路隧道，绕过了臭名昭著的罗坦山口（Rohtang Pass）。
India has already built a 9 km long road tunnel in
the Himalayas, bypassing the notorious Rotang Pass.
阿塔尔隧道（Atal Tunnel）海拔逾10,000英尺，
With an altitude of over 10,000 ft, the
将马纳利小镇（Manali）与两侧山谷之间的通行时间缩短了4小时以上。
atal tunnel has cut travel times between the town of Manally and this pair of valleys by more than 4 hours.
但即便如此，建设过程依然充满挑战。
But even this had its challenges.
隧道需穿越一处断层带，
It meant digging through a fault zone, and
施工期间每分钟最多有8,000升地下水涌入。
there were points where up to 8,000 L of water a minute were coming into the tunnel.
这一切都要求施工方保持极度谨慎。
It all meant they had to be really, really careful.
其中有600米的路段，花了整整4年才打通。
One 600 m stretch took them 4 years to get through.
然而，多个项目屡屡惊出一身冷汗，
The fact there have been these scary moments on multiple projects hasn't
也没能阻止印度继续向喜马拉雅推进更多隧道工程——事实恰恰相反。
been enough to stop India building any more tunnels into the Himalayas. In
fact, it's quite the opposite.
在更西北方，一片因多重原因而更为险峻的地区，
Further to the northwest, in
还有19个项目正在筹备。
a region that's even more hostile for several reasons, there's another 19 projects in the pipeline.
这里指的是拉达克（Ladakh）
We're talking about Lark and the Union territories of
以及查谟和克什米尔（Jammu and Kashmir）联合直辖区——数十年来一直是
Jammu and Kashmir, which
印度、巴基斯坦和中国争议的焦点。
has been the subject of disputes between India, Pakistan, and China for decades.
这一地区基础设施严重不足，原因显而易见——修建这些连接本身就极为棘手。
It's an area that's understandably not well connected because
building those connections is kind of tricky.
往来于各地之间，意味着不得不走那些迂回曲折、险象环生的山路。
Traveling between these places means taking
one of these long winding roads, all of which are pretty treacherous.
就拿兹格拉山口（Ziggilla Pass）来说，
Like the Ziggilla Pass, for example,
沿最险峻路段行驶一趟就要花上4个小时
a trip along the worst part of it can take up to 4 hours,
——这正是他们如今动工建造佐吉拉隧道（Zojilla Tunnel）的原因。
which is why they're now building this, the Zojilla tunnel.
这条隧道在海拔近12,000英尺的高处施工，
Under construction almost 12,000 ft above sea level,
建成后将把这段旅程压缩至仅15分钟。
it'll bring that journey time down to just 15 minutes.
由于是地下隧道，这条路全年畅通无阻。
And because it's subterranean, the road can be used all year round.
更令人印象深刻的是，
If that wasn't already impressive,
这还将成为印度有史以来最长的隧道，全长13公里。
this is also set to be the longest tunnel ever built in India, stretching
to 13 kilometers.
迄今为止，工程尚未发生重大事故
So far, there have been no major catastrophes, which
——这或许与他们选择的隧道施工工法不无关系。
could be to do with the tunneling technique they've chosen.
承包商Mega Engineering & Infrastructures采用了"新奥法"（New Austrian Tunneling Method，NATM）。
Contractor, Mega Engineering, and Infrastructures opted for what's called the new Austrian tunneling method.
这种工法尽可能利用围岩自身的承载能力，
It's where the strength of the surrounding material is utilized as much as possible
并对地层稳定性进行持续监测。
with ground stability monitored continuously.
施工涉及爆破，
Blasting is involved, but
但辅以岩石锚杆（rock bolts）、钢拱架或钢网
support is provided in the form of rock bolts, steel ribs or mesh, and
以及喷射混凝土（shotcrete）等支护手段。
shockrete.
如果你从未听说过喷射混凝土，
If you've never heard of that, it's
它是一种在开挖后立即喷涂到隧道壁上的混凝土。
a type of concrete that's sprayed onto the tunnel walls immediately after excavation.
随后，隧道将完成防水衬砌，
The tunnel is then finished off with a waterproof lining
再覆盖一层混凝土。
followed by another layer of concrete.
需要说明的是，这种工法并非佐吉拉隧道的专利。
Now, we should clarify here that this method isn't unique to the Zodilla tunnel.
事实上，整个地区的多个项目都采用了这种方法，
In fact, it's been chosen for projects across the region, including
包括那条发生坍塌的隧道。
on the one that collapsed.
但正如阿诺德所说，
But as Arnold said, being
能够在问题出现时随时调整方案，本来就是施工的题中之义
able to adjust the approach as and when problems occur is
——而这恰恰是过去没能有效做到的。
all part of it, which perhaps wasn't done effectively in the past.
此外，工程中还部署了其他隧道技术，
Other tunneling techniques have been deployed as well, including
包括在地势较低区域修建的8条明挖法隧道（cut and cover tunnels）。
eight cut and cover tunnels through the more low-lying areas.
这种工法先在地面挖开沟槽，
These are made by first digging a trench in the ground, constructing
在槽内构筑隧道衬砌，
the tunnel lining inside, and
再从上方回填土方。
then back filling over the top.
与此同时，主隧道沿线
Meanwhile, in the main tunnel,
还设有3口竖井（vertical shafts），最深达500米，
three vertical shafts up to 500 meters in height
用于通风。
are being placed along it to provide ventilation.
其中第一口已经实现了真正意义上的"贯通突破"。
The first has already had a literal breakthrough.
一条导向隧道于2025年7月成功完工，
A pilot tunnel was successfully completed in July 2025, which
此后将逐步扩大至7.5米的设计直径。
will now be gradually enlarged until it reaches the full 7.5 m diameter.
但猜猜怎么了？尽管如此谨慎，
But guess what? Despite all the care that's been taken, despite
尽管配备了高科技设备，
all that high-tech equipment, things
工程进展并没有像所有人希望的那样顺利。
haven't gone as smoothly as everyone would have liked.
虽然已完工逾40%，
Although it's now more than 40% complete, this
这条隧道依然困难重重，这也解释了为何原定2026年12月的竣工期限
tunnel has had its fair share of obstacles, which
如今被推迟了整整4年。
explains why the original deadline of December 2026 has now been pushed back by 4 years.
[snorts]
再说回锡尔基亚拉隧道
Back to the Silkier Tunnel, and
——2025年带来了好消息。
2025 has seen the news take a more positive turn.
4月，隧道两端终于在中间相遇，
In April, the two ends finally met in the middle, bringing
开挖工作宣告完成。
excavation work to an end.
尽管如此，
And yet, despite that milestone, there's
距离全线完工仍有很长的路要走。
still a long way to go until it's completely finished.
但话说回来，经历了这一切，
Still, after what happened, having
多等一段时间才能通车，
to wait a little bit longer for it to open is
与当初可能发生的最坏情形相比，实在算不了什么。
nothing compared to what might have been.
这简直不可思议。
It's insane.
"像这样的事，我都不敢相信是真的，但它就是真的。"
Like, I can't believe it's true, but it is true.
"我们确实创造了一个奇迹。"
And we did perform a bit of a miracle.
"我想我记得，事后我遇到了那批工人，才发现他们真的很年轻，"
I think I know when I I met a whole lot of the kids afterwards,
"都只是些孩子。
cuz they're just kids.
我当时想，'Oh my god，
I was like, "Oh my god,
我们真的给了41个人第二次生命。'"
we really have given 41 people a second chance at life."
我们见过在相似地形中修建隧道、没有发生严重事故的案例。
We've seen tunnels built through similar terrain before without serious incidents.
这些尝试告诉我们，
These attempts show us that
在喜马拉雅修建基础设施，其难度远超许多人的想象。
building infrastructure in the Himalayas is more difficult than many could imagine.
随着这些灾难成为历史，
With those calamities now in the past, India
印度必须证明，它能够驾驭这片无情的山地，
must prove that it can tame this unforgiving landscape by
并在更高的赌注下赢得胜利。
taking the stakes even higher.
只希望山脉不会另有打算。
Let's just hope the mountains don't have other ideas.
>> [snorts]
>>
别忘了，我们正通过"建设心理健康"倡议（Get Construction Talking initiative）为建筑行业的心理健康危机发声、
Don't forget that we're raising awareness of construction's mental health crisis
支持相关慈善机构。
and supporting charities in this space through our get construction initiative. You
欢迎访问 getconstructionalking.org 了解更多信息，并找到支持链接。
can learn more and find links to support over at getconstructionalking.org.
一如既往，
And as always guys,
如果你喜欢这个视频，
if you enjoyed this video
想要获取更多来自全球权威建筑视频频道的内容，
and you want to get more from the definitive video channel for construction, make
请确保已订阅 The B1M。
sure you're subscribed to the B1M.